Guide to the Stanford Architecture Collection SC0831
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford architecture collection
1886-2005
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Turner, Paul Venable
SC0831
4 Linear Feet
This collection pertains to Turner's research and writing on the architecture of Stanford University, focusing primarily on the Quad, the museum, and Hanna House, designed by Frank Lloyd Wright. Included are photocopies of research documents, articles, copy prints of historic photographs, modern photographs, reports, correspondence, drafts of Turner's writings and the final publications. Hanna House materials are largely about seismic repairs following the 1989 Loma Prieta earthquake. There are a few original historic documents in the collection, including the 1886 booklet THE LELAND STANFORD JR. UNIVERSITY MUSEUM ORIGIN AND DESCRIPTION; Lorenz Eitner's, "The Development of the Stanford Museum 1964-1984"; and an 1887 print "The Leland Stanford Junior University Now in the Course of Construction at Palo Alto, Cala."
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Paul V. Turner, trained as an architect and art historian, has been on the faculty of Stanford's Dept. of Art and Art History since 1971. His publications include THE EDUCATION OF LE CORBUSIER; THE FOUNDERS & THE ARCHITECTS: THE DESIGN OF STANFORD UNIVERSITY; and CAMPUS: AN AMERICAN PLANNING TRADITION. He chaired the university committee overseeing the repair of Frank Lloyd Wright's Hanna House, badly damaged in the 1989 Loma Prieta earthquake, and in 2001 received the Lloyd W. Dinkelspiel Award for distinctive contributions to undergraduate education.
Description of the Collection
This collection pertains to Turner's research and writing on the architecture of Stanford University, focusing primarily on the Quad, the museum, and Hanna House, designed by Frank Lloyd Wright. Included are photocopies of research documents, articles, copy prints of historic photographs, modern photographs, reports, correspondence, drafts of Turner's writings and the final publications. Hanna House materials are largely about seismic repairs following the 1989 Loma Prieta earthquake. There are a few original historic documents in the collection, including the 1886 booklet THE LELAND STANFORD JR. UNIVERSITY MUSEUM ORIGIN AND DESCRIPTION; Lorenz Eitner's, "The Development of the Stanford Museum 1964-1984"; and an 1887 print "The Leland Stanford Junior University Now in the Course of Construction at Palo Alto, Cala."
Paul R. Hanna House (Stanford, Calif.); Turner, Paul Venable; Turner, Paul Venable; Stanford University. Museum of Art; Eitner, Lorenz.
- Records
  - Photographs - Quad
    - Copy prints: Memorial Arch frieze (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Copy prints: assorted buildings (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Copy prints: views of Stanford land ca. 1887 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Copy prints: miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous negatives (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, miscellaneous, some with negatives (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Copy prints: plans, drawings for Stanford University (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Copy prints: Stanford buildings (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Copy prints: Stanford maps (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Copy prints: non-Stanford buildings (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Negatives (35mm) of historic images and photographs (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs - Museum
    - Negatives (35mm), miscellaneous images (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs – Hanna House
    - Color photos (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Photograph of exterior by Norris Pope, with accompanying note, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Photographs of opening reception and donor dinner, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Copy prints from Hanna House Collection in Stanford University Archives (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photographs and slides of reconstruction/seismic repair, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Quad
    - Stanford chronology for 1883-1892 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Copies of Olmsted correspondence, 1887-1910, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Birds-Eye rendering of Stanford quad (difference versions, question of authorship, etc.) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Possible Stanford influence on other buildings and institutions (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Stanford architecture exhibition (Art Gallery) 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Inventory of Stanford University drawings (Olmsted Historic Site holdings) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Research images – 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Research images – 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Research images – 3 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Research sources – issues of The Sequoia 1895 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Research sources – Mary Jo McNamara, "The Memorial Frieze: Its Iconography and Sources" (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Research sources – 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Research sources – 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Research sources – 3 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Research sources – 4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Founders and Architects – correspondence, 1976-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Stanford architectural research – correspondence, 1975-83 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Museum
    - Essay text and plans, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Essay text with revisions (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - The Leland Stanford Jr. University Museum. Origin and Description. 1886 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Research materials (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Eitner, Lorenz, "The Development of the Stanford Museum 1964-1984" (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Ernest Ransome (and Percy & Hamilton) (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Construction using whaler forming systems (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Report: Damage to Unreinforced Masonry Buildings at Stanford University in the 1906 San Francisco Earthquake by Gretchen W. Smith and Robert Reitherman, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous research (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - American museums (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Athens museum and other European museums (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Stanford University, other buildings
    - Library (1905) – source materials (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Library (1905) – Imprint article and correspondence, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - List of Stanford buildings, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Articles by Turner (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Lewis Mumford at Stanford (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Stanford family and the university in general (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Hanna House
    - Documents from Laura Jones (Planning Office), 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Documents from Laura Jones (Planning Office), 2002-2004 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Documents from Laura Jones (Planning Office) – furnishings, 2003-2005 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Documents from Laura Jones (Planning Office) – floors, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Documents from Laura Jones (Planning Office) – lighting, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Recommendations for Seismic Repair and Conservation of Historic Features, Final Report (Architectural Resources Group), February 1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Turner, Frank, Lloyd Wright's Hanna House Restored [SU booklet 1999] (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Booklet published by The Stanford Restoration Fund (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous information (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Article for Development Office – text and correspondence, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Article – drafts, notes, and correspondence, 1998-99 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Book project with Bret Lizundia and John Burton (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Board of Governors, 1987-89 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Morley Baer photo collection in S.U. Archives (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Hanna House papers in S. U. Archives (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - FLW and earthquake design (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Articles (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and other materials, 1994-99 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Oya-stone urn (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with Paul and Jean Hanna and related material, 1980-99 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - T-shirt design (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Furnishings (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Furnishings – inventory 2004 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Oversized materials
    - Print: The Leland Stanford Junior University Now in the Course of Construction at Palo Alto, Cala. Issued with the Christmas Number San Francisco News Letter, 1887 [same as SUA Print 016.1] (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous oversized photographs and copied documents (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Matted negatives for printing, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - A. B. Clark, Art Principles in House, Furniture, and Village Building (1921) – photocopied at 112% enlargement (Box 7, Folder 4)